<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jetroid's Blog</title>
    <description>The personal site for Jet 'Jetroid' Holt</description>
    <link>https://jetholt.com</link>
    <atom:link href="https://jetholt.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>June 2020 Micro-Posts</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today marks the second month since I started (trying to) publish a ‘micro post’ every day. You can read more about &lt;a href=&quot;/may-2020-microblogs/&quot;&gt;why I’m doing that by clicking here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, I’m trying to publish something - anything - every day. Broadly speaking, the goal is to be more frequent with my uploads and to gradually get better at writing too. If anything, it’s just good to exercise the ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AndreyAzimov/status/1135938608420929536&quot;&gt;finishing muscle&lt;/a&gt;’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As promised, because this is the end of the month, I’m publishing a round-up post that includes links to all of this month’s micro posts. You can find the links below the text, as well as a small excerpt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how am I doing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;frequency&quot;&gt;Frequency&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By my count, I wrote 23 micro posts this month, which means I missed about a week’s worth of posts! That’s much worse than May, where I only missed 1 day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, I also wrote my &lt;a href=&quot;/climbing-the-bali-mountains/&quot;&gt;Climbing the Bali Mountains&lt;/a&gt; post, which took long enough to write that I didn’t feel like I needed to write a micro post on that day. The post was effectively the length of several micro posts!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So all told, I’m pleased with my results this month. There are a few posts which feel a bit ranty and that I’m not exactly proud of, but that probably just means I needed to get something out of my system. I’m still publishing posts that don’t necessarily meet my mark because that’s the whole point of my micro posts. Publishing helps me keep up a momentum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Maybe publishing just to publish seems inane to you, but by &lt;a href=&quot;/starting-many-things/&quot;&gt;starting many things&lt;/a&gt;, I believe I’m able to find the things that I really want to write about.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;quality&quot;&gt;Quality&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Has my quality of writing improved?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hard to say, but my gut feeling is no; two months probably isn’t long enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&quot;/stranger-in-a-strange-land/&quot;&gt;stranger in a strange land&lt;/a&gt; post started as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=23543043&quot;&gt;comment on hacker news&lt;/a&gt;. People there seemed to really like what I wrote. I think my artistic language managed to tap into people’s own feelings and emotions (and probably nostalgia, given that almost nobody is travelling right now).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’d say that I can be pretty good at writing feelings-driven prose. The posts where I felt most passionate are certainly the ones that are most interesting to re-read, at least for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure if I’m capable of that with my longer-form posts, as I get burned out quickly and I’m not sure that I’m maintaining my reader’s interest all the way through…&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2020 17:23:06 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://jetholt.com/june-2020-microposts/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jetholt.com/june-2020-microposts/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Climbing the Bali Mountains</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A year ago today, I climbed Mt Abang in Bali. Seven months later, I climbed Mt Batur. I didn’t write about either adventure at the time, so I have to write it now to share the story of the trip. Enjoy!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;climbing-mt-abang&quot;&gt;Climbing Mt Abang&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a lot of fun to ride across the landscape of Bali in the dark. We had left home at 2:30AM n the 8th June 2019, and I was incredibly excited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The roads were empty and the air was refreshingly cool. After being in Asia for 6 months, it was nice to be outdoors and not feel hot and sticky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was incredibly quiet and peaceful on the journey. We were mostly alone and didn’t see any other people, though occasionally we’d pass through a village and see villagers selling things at a market - at 4AM! Life just starts earlier in Bali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/bali-mountain-villagers.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Villagers attending a market at 4AM.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Villagers attending a market at 4AM.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We met up with the rest of the group just after 5:30AM. That seemed appropriate, given that we would be climbing the mountain with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/lensa_5.30/&quot;&gt;lensa_5.30&lt;/a&gt; running club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Museum+Geopark+Batur/@-8.2837608,115.3647121,200m&quot;&gt;Museum Geopark&lt;/a&gt; building loomed in the fog and felt pretty ominous to me. We stopped there and posed for photos as a group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/bali-mountain-geopark.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Museum Geopark looming in the fog.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Museum Geopark looming in the fog.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/bali-mountain-posing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lensa 5.30 posing for a photo.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Lensa 5.30 posing for a photo.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chill of the cold air at the base of the mountain was fun, too. The temperature was around 14-16 Celsius, and my companions were complaining about how cold it was whilst shivering. I remarked that the UK was at that temperature or below for two thirds of the year. They stared in disbelief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We drove a little further to a wooded area where you can park and then enter directly on to the trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stopped at two different temple spots as we ascended. I say temples because that’s what my Balinese comrades referred to it as, but I would probably have called them ‘shrines’. Everyone made offerings before we continued to climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/bali-mountain-shrine.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;One of the temple shrines that we stopped at.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;One of the temple shrines that we stopped at.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you have already seen, it was very misty on that morning, so despite reaching many clearings that could have provided astonishing views, we didn’t see much on the ascent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/bali-mountain-side.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The misty and cloudy view from the mountainside.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The misty and cloudy view from the mountainside.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I enjoyed looking at the flora. The foliage was really interesting. It didn’t exactly feel like the kind of stuff I’d seen in the rest of the jungles on Bali, but more like a mix between what I might find at home with some distinctly tropical plants mixed in too. I’m sure the climate contributed to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/bali-mountain-foliage.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lichen growing on a tree, cobwebs, greenery. This photo has it all.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Lichen growing on a tree, cobwebs, greenery. This photo has it all.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/bali-mountain-trees.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The trees were tall and imposing.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The trees were tall and imposing.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/bali-mountain-climb.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;It wasn't raining, but the mist and humidity made our hair and clothes damp.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;It wasn’t raining, but the mist and humidity made our hair and clothes damp.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually we reached the summit of the mountain, 2151m above sea level. It was still incredibly cloudy, so we couldn’t really see much, which was a shame. Occasionally we got a glimpse of the land below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/bali-mountain-summit.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;At the summit of Mt. Abang, 2151m above sea level.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;At the summit of Mt. Abang, 2151m above sea level.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During our climb, I had trouble getting purchase on the damp mud and slippery soil a few times. This wasn’t too bad on the climb up, but on the way down, I slipped repeatedly. It was really embarrassing for me and I felt like I was letting down my culture and representing the west in a bad way. In truth, it was because my trainers were worn down and flat from the hundreds of kilometres of running that I had done in the sixth months since I had bought my shoes. But nobody believed that excuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/bali-mountain-slipping.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Struggling to make my way down an incline.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Struggling to make my way down an incline.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst descending, the mist and clouds cleared somewhat, so we could see the view. There were only a few clear spots because of the dense foliage, but every time there was a view, we stopped. It was breathtaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/bali-mountain-view-from-abang.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The view from the mountainside.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The view from the mountainside.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could also see Mount Batur, the neighbouring mountain. You can see it on the far side of the lake, above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Let’s go there next time I come to Bali”, I told Ni. She agreed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;climbing-mt-batur&quot;&gt;Climbing Mt Batur&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friend Aiden had recommended that I climb Batur when I had first arrived in Bali. He had told me that the sunrise from Batur was beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next opportunity to climb a mountain was when I returned to Bali for two months in December 2019. We didn’t want to climb too close to Christmas or New Year because it would be crowded, (actually, I really, really wanted to &lt;a href=&quot;/hiking-new-year/&quot;&gt;climb on New Years Day&lt;/a&gt;, but Ni wouldn’t let me.), so we waited until the 19th January 2020. Again, we got up at 2AM to travel the 40km to Batur. Again, we reached the base of the mountain around 5AM and met up with the rest of the group at the Geopark Museum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we arrived at the base of the mountain proper, a group of guys accosted us and demanded we pay up to climb the mountain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were travelling in a group of 11; 10 locals and me. They wanted to charge the locals Rp5000 each,
and charge me Rp500,000 (because I was a foreigner). That’s $36/£30/€32.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t even believe those guys were official, and didn’t want to pay. I’ve heard about scammers trying to get money from people to visit Besakih temple, and I was almost certain this was the same thing. There were no uniforms to be seen. I definitely wouldn’t have paid because I didn’t believe it, but Koko, the group leader, haggled them down to Rp300,000 and agreed to split the cost across the group. It ruined our mood, but fine. I paid Koko Rp80,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;youtube&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nQxepC0Jm9U&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we neared the mountain, we could see a trail of lights blinking all over the side of the mountain. Imagine a vein of light going up the mountain. I initially thought that the trail was lit, but quickly realised that it was the smartphone torches of the other visitors who were all following the same path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Batur was much less jungle-y and much more rocky than Abang. It just had grasses and a few bushes here and there, rather than big trees everywhere. That made it much better for the views. As we began to climb, the sun began to rise and we captured the most beautiful photos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/bali-mountain-sunrise.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sunrise over Mt Abang, viewed from Mt Batur.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Sunrise over Mt Abang, viewed from Mt Batur.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/bali-mountain-ni-superhero.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ni standing like a hero.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Ni standing like a hero.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/bali-mountain-sign.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Surprisingly, this fancy monument was not at the summit of Batur.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Surprisingly, this fancy monument was not at the summit of Batur.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The climb was fairly easy. When we reached the top, monkeys appeared out of nowhere and stole a banana from Ni. They liked to sit on a tin roof of a small coffee shack, staying alert for vulnerable tourists eating and drinking food that they could steal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/bali-mountain-monkeyroof.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Monkeys enjoying their stolen goods&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Monkeys enjoying their stolen goods.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/bali-mountain-stolen-banana.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Monkey eating Ni's stolen Banana.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Monkey eating Ni’s stolen Banana.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we navigated the mountain, I was informed that the mountain was actually an active volcano and we
were walking along the rim of the caldera. Woah, I had no idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/bali-mountain-caldera.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Looking down into the Caldera.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Looking down into the Caldera.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our group pointed out big plumes of steam from where the volcano was heating the earth. There were a few holes in the ground that you could put your hand into to feel the heat too, and in some places locals were actually boiling water. I then realised that the few coffee shacks that we had passed were using water heated by volcano heat. Cool, volcano coffee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/bali-mountain-monkey-family.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A family of monkeys took over all of the benches.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A family of monkeys took over all of the benches.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We made it down safely too, and I didn’t have any major falls or stumbles. Unlike during my trip to Abang, this time I was wearing brand new shoes. I was able to prove to Ni and the rest of the group that I wasn’t just a clumsy foreigner. I was just a foreigner who didn’t buy new shoes often enough. Incidentally during the descent a bunch of gravel rocks cut up my shoes and damaged them a lot. Oops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the way home, we were both so tired. I almost fell asleep several times whilst on the bike, which would be extremely dangerous. In the end Ni had to practice Indonesian words with me to help me focus and stay awake. Or stopping from time for time to get me to run up a hill or do star jumps or something. I cannot overstate how sleepy and drowsy I was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ni edited a video using footage that I recorded of the adventure to Batur. It isn’t how I would have edited it, but you can watch it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/B9Q8U_xJEeF/&quot;&gt;on instagram here&lt;/a&gt;, or watch the version that I reuploaded to youtube, below. If you’re happy to watch it on Instagram, please watch it there and give Ni your support!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;youtube&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IV3TDv8wMRs&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 16:06:58 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://jetholt.com/climbing-the-bali-mountains/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jetholt.com/climbing-the-bali-mountains/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>May 2020 Micro Posts</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m going to be trying to write more to this website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, I try to aim for a certain standard of quality in my writing, and this can really hold me up from writing about something I want to write about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it takes a week &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;or more&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; just to write &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; post. Yeah, perfection is killer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It gets worse when I add images, because I agonise over them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m going to be writing more things to a lower quality. I’m calling these ‘Micro’ posts, and you can find a full list here: &lt;a href=&quot;/micro/&quot;&gt;Micro&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will be just what I’m thinking about, or some small observations, or whatever. Generally without pictures, without proofreading, without rewording each sentence hundreds of times. Almost as if I have a typewriter and a stream of conciousness - no going back to make changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re struggling to understand the difference, compare the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cad-comic.com/&quot;&gt;Ctrl + Alt + Del&lt;/a&gt; webcomic with it’s “Micro” webcomic, &lt;a href=&quot;https://cad-comic.com/category/sillies/&quot;&gt;Sillies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because these posts will (probably) be of a lower quality to what I’d usually put out, I’m categorising them differently. Only the most recent few will show on the homepage (and also won’t have images dedicated to them!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of each month, I’ll publish a monthly summary that has links to all of the micro posts from that month, as well some writing at the top (like you’re reading now!) that might include some reflections on the month. Or maybe I won’t write anything there at all sometimes. Who knows?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t be sending out emails for every micro post either, though I will for the monthly summaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Micro posts and monthly summaries will not be considered as a ‘&lt;a href=&quot;/latest/&quot;&gt;latest&lt;/a&gt;’ post. Instead, I have created a new url, for &lt;a href=&quot;/latestmicro/&quot;&gt;latest micro posts&lt;/a&gt;. Hopefully that we be useful for people who like to bookmark things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, everything I write (regular posts and also micro posts) will appear on the &lt;a href=&quot;/archive/&quot;&gt;archive&lt;/a&gt; page. Micro posts will appear in a smaller font.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2020 18:38:06 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://jetholt.com/may-2020-microblogs/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jetholt.com/may-2020-microblogs/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Repatriated</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;After Wuhan - a city the size of New York - got locked down, I began to pay special attention to the news about the ‘novel coronavirus’. I was far from home whilst the situation developed, visiting Indonesia and later Malaysia. Being on the other side of the world during what quickly became a massively disruptive global crisis was very scary, so I eventually made the call to fly home.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Coronavirus first became a big news story, I was in Indonesia with my girlfriend. Every day she would ask me “What is the latest news on the virus?” and I’d be able to tell her the latest headlines without having to look them up: “China broke 28,000 cases today.”, or “First confirmed cases in the United Kingdom”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/lockdown-indonesia.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;In Indonesia with few fears, two days before Wuhan locked down.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;In Indonesia with few fears, two days before Wuhan locked down.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excluding China, it initially looked like there were just a few isolated cases being spread internationally. These cases seemed to be caught fairly early on, with contact tracing preventing further spread. The world seemed to be doing a good job of containing the outbreak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly that assumption was wrong and things started going wrong. The problem escalated. Meanwhile, I carried on with my schedule and transferred to Malaysia in early February.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that China was taking drastic actions made me believe things were serious. You don’t lock down a city - and later a whole region - like that for no reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn’t sure what the best course of action would be for myself moving forward. If I had a permanent home base I’d know exactly what to do - stock up and be careful - but being alone on the other side of the world comes with it’s own set of challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;preparation-has-a-cost&quot;&gt;Preparation Has A Cost&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike folk living in one place, ‘being prepared’ for a traveller has a high cost and is more difficult. Worse, if preparation turns out to be unnecessary, it can be very wasteful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, whilst staying in Asia, I eat out for every meal. It’s cheaper and easier than cooking, which is often difficult because most hotels are under-equipped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hotel didn’t even have any hobs (cooktops), baking trays, or the like. It only had a single fridge/freezer and two microwaves (one disguised as an oven) to share between all the guests. Curiously, the hotel did have a few saucepans. I think that they must be decorative; there’s no way to heat them safely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I continued to stay at this hotel, my cooking potential would be very limited, so naturally I would prefer to continue eating out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/kl-laptop.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kitchen / living space in my hotel.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Kitchen / living space in my hotel.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to justify ‘stockpiling’ non-perishable food when you live in one place. If you don’t end up needing your stockpile - perhaps because the crisis comes to pass - then that’s fine; you’ll eat it eventually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a traveller chooses to stockpile, they have to consider their purchases. Any uneaten food will be a wasted expense when they move on; you can’t exactly take food on to a plane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of planes, another way a traveller might ‘prepare’ is to temporarily stop being a traveller. They might &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/levelsio/status/1227119922075066368&quot;&gt;choose to fly back to their home country&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That also has risks: if the crisis comes to pass uneventfully, you’ll feel pretty silly to have disrupted your plans and wasted your time and money. Alternatively, the situation might completely flip, and your home country ends up being worse than the one you fled. You’d probably feel &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/levelsio/status/1238267266078322689&quot;&gt;pretty silly then, too&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;decision-paralysis&quot;&gt;Decision Paralysis&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the crisis continued to escalate, it became clear that it wasn’t going to go away uneventfully, and therefore some action or decision was necessary. More and more locations were reporting community spread, and countries like Italy, Iran, and South Korea became hotspots, before spreading massively across Europe and the USA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I almost became paralysed, not knowing what the smart move was. Should I cancel everything and return home? That would mean I probably wouldn’t travel again for a long time; then when would I next see my girlfriend? At the same time, she was considering booking a flight to visit me in Malaysia (and later did book a flight - for April. Naturally, it was cancelled.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really didn’t know what to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/kl-pool-gym.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pool and gym where I spent most of my time.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Pool and gym where I spent most of my time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I watched the figures worsen every day, hoping that things would miraculously resolve. Regretting that I wasn’t doing more to prepare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was really hoping that Malaysia wouldn’t see a spike in cases, and that if it did, that the government wouldn’t do anything too drastic like completely closing the border.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I extended my hotel stay until mid-April, anticipating that hotels might stop accepting bookings without warning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I continued running outdoors, cycling in the gym, and lifting weights. I was trying to become as healthy as I could, so that if I got infected I could beat the virus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;malaysia-locks-down&quot;&gt;Malaysia Locks Down&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In early March, I heard reports that a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tablighi_Jamaat&quot;&gt;Tabligh&lt;/a&gt; event - a Muslim gathering where worshippers live, pray, and sleep in close proximity for many days - was held in Kuala Lumpur, just 7 miles from where I was staying. Early reports indicated that 5000 people had attended during the four day event, though later figures estimated that there may had been as many as 16,000 visitors, some 14,500 of whom were Malaysian nationals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nst.com.my/news/nation/2020/03/573835/malaysian-tabligh-gathering-tested-positive-covid-19&quot;&gt;Someone who had attended inevitably tested positive&lt;/a&gt;. My stomach dropped as I realised the possibilities, thinking back to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shincheonji_Church_of_Jesus#Association_with_the_coronavirus_outbreak&quot;&gt;Shincheonji Church&lt;/a&gt; that had caused South Korea to become a hotspot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why was this event allowed to go ahead?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt dread; before this, Malaysia had seen only a few cases according to the official statistics, and all of them had been discharged. After the Tabligh event, there were suddenly 100 or 200 new cases every day, and the country quickly responded by going into lockdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/lockdown-outside.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo taken on the evening before the lockdown. My last chance to be outside and free for some time.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Photo taken on the evening before the lockdown. My last chance to be outside and free for some time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason, after the lockdown was announced, I was more concerned about the fact that my gym would be closing than I was about the virus. I had just booked a month pass a few days earlier and wouldn’t be able to use the space or get a refund. It was a silly reaction, in retrospect, but I think my brain was struggling to come to terms with what was happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With one day’s notice before the lockdown took effect, I went between the various local supermarkets to try to buy food. Predictably, they were very busy. Some items were completely out of stock, but it didn’t seem to be as extreme as I had seen my friends and family in Europe and the US reporting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/lockdown-supplies.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Supplies to eat during the lockdown.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Supplies to eat during the lockdown.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought enough food to last an estimated two weeks or more. I made several trips, filling my backpack with nuts, cereals, wraps, canned vegetables, canned soups, and chutneys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-decision&quot;&gt;The Decision&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was obvious by mid-to-late March that this crisis wasn’t going to go away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Europe had become the epicenter, and my government in particular &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/mar/15/the-governments-herd-immunity-plan-is-callous-and-dangerous&quot;&gt;were approaching things very badly&lt;/a&gt;. Meanwhile, many countries in Asia were doing a comparatively good job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was happy to see that the Kuala Lumpurians seemed to mostly obey the lockdown. The normally busy road outside my hotel was very quiet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;youtube&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GeAARY9auEE&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps selfishly, I had been considering riding out the storm in Asia. I was contemplating sheltering in place until I had to leave, then flying to nearby countries that were doing a good job of containment like South Korea or Singapore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still had a month and a half remaining on my Malaysia visa, so wouldn’t have had to leave the country until early May (as long as I could keep booking into hotels).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, I noticed that more and more countries were completely forbidding entry to foreigners, and I wondered: “What will happen when my visa does finally expire?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.emirates.com/media-centre/the-emirates-groups-business-response-to-covid-19-updated/&quot;&gt;Airlines were ceasing to operate&lt;/a&gt;, flights were being cancelled, and there were reports that some airports were closing. I feared that I might come to a point where no nearby foreign nations would accept me, but could not travel to my home country because all of the routes were closed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, my family unanimously asked me to return (or hinted very strongly that they thought I should). In particular, my father had said one thing that greatly influenced my choice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Being a visitor is not the same as being a citizen.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That wasn’t something I had considered, and it was very true and very scary. If things got crazy, I wouldn’t be a priority to the government of wherever I was staying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to bite the bullet and fly home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;waiting-to-return&quot;&gt;Waiting To Return&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seemed like insanity that I was voluntarily choosing to go somewhere that was being hit harder than where I was currently located (and at the time I made the decision, the UK hadn’t even entered any lockdown measures yet!). The UK had 6x more recorded cases than Malaysia, which meant that the UK was several weeks ahead. At the time of writing, more than two weeks since I made my decision, Malaysia still hasn’t officially caught up with the number of cases that the UK was seeing at that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankly, I felt anxious about flying at all. Yes, it would be safer to be at home &lt;em&gt;long term&lt;/em&gt;, but there were still significant &lt;em&gt;short term&lt;/em&gt; risks involved with getting home. Most of the available journeys were 24 hour to 36 hour trips. These long stints in confined metal tubes meant many potential opportunities to become infected. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rDdqifhua8k&quot;&gt;I thought about World War Z&lt;/a&gt;; just one zombie infected the whole plane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I booked a flight for the 26th March. I was able to find one with “just” 18 hours total travel time, flying with Qatar Airways and transiting through Doha before landing in Manchester Airport. My sister would pick me up from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The few days whilst I waited to fly were uneventful, but very stressful. My government instituted a lockdown and were repeatedly warning that &lt;a href=&quot;https://metro.co.uk/2020/03/23/british-travellers-told-return-uk-now-12444831/&quot;&gt;all British travellers should return home&lt;/a&gt;, whilst airports warned that they &lt;a href=&quot;https://uk.reuters.com/article/uk-health-coronavirus-britain-airports/uks-biggest-airports-ask-for-help-as-possible-closure-looms-idUKKBN2141WH&quot;&gt;may close without government help&lt;/a&gt;. I’d repeatedly check to see that my flights were still operating and that the three airports were all still open. I really didn’t want to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aljazeera.com/news/2020/03/tourists-limbo-kuala-lumpur-airport-coronavirus-shutdown-200325103528530.html&quot;&gt;trapped in limbo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that I couldn’t exercise in my gym, I had begun to workout in my hotel room. I used my resistance bands (and calisthenics) to replace weightlifting, and replaced my regular runs with ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/3200843469&quot;&gt;Quarantine Walks&lt;/a&gt;’ (where I &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/3208185573&quot;&gt;walked around my hotel&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/3213960402&quot;&gt;a big loop&lt;/a&gt; for an hour or two after midnight). Neither felt adequate, but they were better than nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/lockdown-space.png&quot; alt=&quot;Spaces available to me during the lockdown.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Spaces available to me during the lockdown. Green is where I slept, Yellow indicates the space where I did my ‘quarantine walks’, and Blue is other spaces I had access to.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;kl-ghost-town&quot;&gt;KL Ghost Town&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the day I was due to fly, Kuala Lumpur had already been on lockdown for a week and a half, and I’d spent it entirely indoors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My flight wasn’t until 2AM, but the 10PM curfew that had been imposed with the lockdown meant that I had needed to checkout earlier to get to the airport on time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to leave my hotel at 8PM, catch the monorail to KL Sentral, then take the train to the airport. Out of curiosity, I decided to take the monorail from Bukit Bintang - essentially the Times Square of Kuala Lumpur - rather than the nearest stop. Bukit Bintang wasn’t a far walk, so no pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/lockdown-bb.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bukit Bintang, uncharacteristically empty.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Bukit Bintang, uncharacteristically empty.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was quite strange to wander through the city and see how much of a ghost town some places had become. In my experience, Bukit Bintang never really sleeps. I went through the area a few times during my &lt;a href=&quot;/4x4x48/&quot;&gt;4x4x48 running challenge&lt;/a&gt;, and it was lively and busy even at 4AM. During the lockdown, I only saw security guards. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/flowen_nl/status/1241183775775576064&quot;&gt;Eerie&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reflected that this would be the perfect time to take pictures of world monuments and heritage sites. Maybe one day, when we all have vaccines and TARDISes, hmm?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monorail was mostly empty. Some seats were blocked off to encourage people to keep their distance, but that was hardly necessary - I had half a carriage to myself! I was careful to avoid touching anything, and instead just enjoyed the ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/lockdown-monorail.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Deserted Kuala Lumpur Monorail during Coronavirus Lockdown.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Deserted Kuala Lumpur Monorail.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KL Sentral is usually one of the pulsing hearts of Kuala Lumpur. It’s the only real direct transit hub that links to the airport, and there’s a large, 8 floor mall called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.klsentral.info/top-10-shopping-kl-sentral/nu-sentral/directory/&quot;&gt;Nu Sentral&lt;/a&gt; right next door.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, KL Sentral was also a ghost town. I literally only saw three people: A security guard in the mall, and the two guys who sold me my train ticket to the airport. The mall was cordoned off so that you could only transit through between the monorail and the train station, and it felt like I in some kind of zombie apocalypse to see it so empty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/lockdown-nusentral.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Deserted Nu Sentral Mall during Coronavirus Lockdown.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Deserted Nu Sentral Mall.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with the Monorail, the train was also almost completely empty, which shocked me as it has always been completely full in the past. Just how empty must the airport be right now? I even started to get worried that the airport was closed and that I’d somehow missed the announcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/lockdown-train.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Deserted KL Ekspres Train during Coronavirus Lockdown.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Deserted KL Ekspres Train.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;airport-rodeo&quot;&gt;Airport Rodeo&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, the airport was open, but predictably very quiet. I got thermal scanned before being allowed into the check-in area, though I wasn’t allowed to check in to my flight for a few hours, leaving me to wait in a quiet corner of the airport and watch &lt;em&gt;Cast Away&lt;/em&gt; alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst walking, I took a glance at the flight schedule board, and was shocked to see the sheer number of cancelled flights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/lockdown-board.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Board showing cancelled flights in KLIA airport.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Board showing cancelled flights in KLIA airport.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Checking in was a somewhat stressful experience. The passengers whom had arrived to check in before me were in a tightly packed queue, whereas I wanted to maintain a 2m distance. New people assumed I wasn’t part of the queue and kept queuing in front of me, and I’d have to point them to the back. They generally weren’t very happy about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;Yes, I know that I would soon be on the same flight as them, and therefore breathing the same recycled air, but planes have HEPA filters to try to combat infection. Additionally, those particular people might not be close to me at all. I’d just feel safer to limit my overall exposure.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/lockdown-airport.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ever seen a major airport be this empty?&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Ever seen a major airport be this empty?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My flights passed uneventfully. I made sure to drink lots of water (and event got a comment about it from a flight attendant), and tried to sleep somewhat. The first plane was a bit over a third full; many people got 3 seats to themselves, and lay across them to sleep. The second was packed - as had been Doha airport - and I hated every minute of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/lockdown-doha.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Packed Doha waiting room.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Packed Doha waiting room. Well… packed for an outbreak, anyway.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a guess, most of the passengers on the second flight (the flight to Manchester) were probably UK citizens who had chosen to leave the UK to travel abroad within the prior two to three weeks. That’s well within the period where it was obvious that travel would not be wise, so I think it’s safe to assume that these people hadn’t been taking the virus seriously and may not have been taking precautions. Few wore masks. I didn’t trust any of them, and I cringed whenever I heard a cough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But eventually it was over, and I was back on British soil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;england&quot;&gt;England&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My sister and her boyfriend picked me up from the airport in Manchester, as planned. We had felt that it would be safer for myself (and others) for me to avoiding the  train, as I was now possibly contagious. Instead, we needed some way to prevent me from infecting my sister. We had the idea (planned whilst I was still in Malaysia) to put up some plastic sheeting between the front and back of the car in an attempt to isolate them from me. It wouldn’t be perfect, but any protection would be good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/lockdown-car.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Quarantine Car. Not perfect, but better than nothing.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Quarantine Car. Not perfect, but better than nothing.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst they applied the sheeting to the car, I tried to decontaminate myself with a bottle of hand sanitiser. I took off my jacket and trousers (I had shorts on underneath), and lathered a tissue with the sanitiser and wiped myself down with it, before wiping my clothes and belongings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually the police arrived and told us to move off, as we were in a high security area. They weren’t willing to wait for us to finish. The sheeting wasn’t fully secure yet, so I had to hold it and better secure it whilst we drove away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the sheet was secure, I continued to try to decontaminate. This might seem like I was overreacting, but there are many people in my family who may be high risk. I was determined to kill any virus - or as much as I could. If my family are going to catch it because of me, I’d prefer to start them off with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?time_continue=845&amp;amp;v=efaDuE-XEi4&quot;&gt;low inoculum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one point, I rubbed sanitiser on my chin, and the fumes caused me to choke. My sister and her boyfriend interpreted this as a Coronavirus cough and started to panic! I’m not sure if they believed my explanations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;home&quot;&gt;Home&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, they dropped me off at my Father’s house. It was a really weird reunion. There was no hugging; usually a sign of a troubled relationship, here a gesture of mutual kindness and respect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three groups - My sister and her boyfriend; me; and my Father - all kept a distance from each other. In these times, we all have to act as if we are infected, to try to prevent infecting others. Especially those who are more at risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Father let me in to the wooden cabin where I would be staying, joking that it was my ‘cell’. They had moved my old bed into the room, and set up a desk and cooking space for me. The cupboards were stocked with a week and a half’s worth of food, and I essentially had everything I needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/lockdown-cabin.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Quarantine is not so bad.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, almost. The cabin lacks a bathroom. In normal times, this wouldn’t be a problem as guests can use the main bathroom inside the house. I had insisted that I wanted to avoid going inside as much as possible, so had proposed that I would bathe on the veranda of the cabin, using my neice’s paddling pool. It’s not overlooked by many other houses, so I have privacy, even if cold and uncomfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the toilet, I have no other option than to use the small downstairs bathroom near the front door inside the house. That sadly means that I risk exposing my parents to the virus (if I have it). I’ve been taking precautions as best I can though, like washing my hands thoroughly before going inside, wearing a face mask every time, and avoiding touching any doorhandles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;now&quot;&gt;Now&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have now spent a week and a half in self isolation in the cabin. Before that, I was indoors for 8 days in Malaysia. I’m showing no virus symptoms, which is good, but I may just be asymptomatic, so will wait out the full 24 days quarantine. There have been ups and downs, but the living situation isn’t too unpleasant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expected that the worst thing would be bathing outside in the paddling pool, but it really isn’t too bad. I’d almost say it’s comparable to being in a very shallow hot tub; it feels cold before and after, but whilst inside, you’re covering your body with warm water, which actually feels very refreshing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve taken the opportunity to dial in on my diet and get back to calorie counting. My parents gave me a small stock of food - enough to last two weeks with calorie restriction - and occasionally give me a few extra items, a cooked meal, or a spare vegetable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/lockdown-food.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tracking my food store.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Tracking my food store.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took stock of everything I was given, noting realistic portion sizes, calories, carbs, fats, and protein. From there I was able to work out how many days I had at different caloric restrictions, as well as how many grams of each macronutrient I could expect to get per day before my food runs out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My protein allowance was looking a little low, so I’ve ordered 5kg of protein powder from Amazon to help me boost that. I also ordered scales so that I can ascertain my weight. Neither have arrived yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d say that there are two things unpleasant about living in the cabin in these circumstances. One has mostly already been rectified, and I’m hoping that once I’ve been isolated for longer I can ease up the other too:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is the climate. The insulation in the cabin isn’t great, meaning the temperature inside mostly reflects the temperature outside. Even with a 2500W oil heater running round the clock, it can get very cold. Particularly in the mornings. We’ve resolved this by purchasing a space heater that I can use sparingly if it’s too cold; I’ve used it twice so far, for ten minutes each, and I have to say it does the trick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately the cold (and perhaps the dehumidifier that I accidentally left running for several days in a row) has led to my hands becoming dry and cracked, perhaps as a symptom of my eczema (though I’ve never had it on my hands before). I suspect that the very cold water that I use to wash my hands (and dishes) isn’t helping. I’ve taken to sleeping with medicated cream on my hands, covered with gloves to stop it spreading everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second unpleasant thing is having to go indoors to use the bathroom. I don’t want to be a burden to my father by constantly interrupting him to let me inside, nor do I want to go inside any more frequently than I have to for risk of contaminating the inside of the house. I’ve occasionally become ‘toilet shy’ because I know that - at least on some level - he knows that I’m in there. It’s just not a great situation for anyone, honestly. I’ve been drinking less liquids just to have to go to the bathroom less. I’m hoping that in a week or two - once we have counted out the quarantine clock - that I will be able to come and go to the bathroom as I please.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post took a surprising amount of time to write.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of things that I chose not to write here; things I was thinking about, concerns I have had; or fears for the present and future. Little has been said about my physical or mental well-being during this period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was difficult discerning which threads of thought were interesting, important, or unique. At this time, everyone has a lockdown story. My generation will tell their grandkids about this, no doubt about it. What unique perspectives do &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; have?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was very stressful being in a far off part of the world during a crisis like this. Living in a hotel means that you’re surrounded by strangers, and you can’t know if they are being safe or not. For example, in early February there was a Chinese guest staying in the hotel who had a persistent cough. It was very concerning to me and a few others, and when I asked him about it, he told me that he had a condition and it was nothing to worry about. Paranoia was rife. I realised later that even my hotel’s ventilation system was probably a risk, as the air might be pushed between different floors of the building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I’m home, the crisis feels very distant. The little cul-de-sac where I live looks the same as always. Quiet. The only people I come in contact with are my parents, but I still see the neighbours gardening from time to time. Just like always.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It almost feels like sleepy Arley is immune, like the Coronavirus won’t come to this place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to see why many young people in my country might flaunt the lockdown rules, or take advantage of their ‘daily exercise’ to chat with their neighbours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The irony is that I’m sure there are people exercising for the first time, just as an excuse to go outside; meanwhile, I’d love to do my regular runs, but am not doing for fear that I might be contagious to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, it’s better for everyone to stay indoors, but I’m sure you’ve heard enough about that by now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to imagine I’m in some far off place, like an arctic research station, or a cabin in the Siberian wilderness. In those places, it’s normal to rarely venture outside, and to only be able to get new supplies a few times a month. The spring cold, and the wind against the cabin roof certainly adds to the illusion. It’s comforting to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know what state the world will be in when this is over. Many people are worried about what the world will be like afterwards. Will their normal lives resume, or will things change forever? That question weighs heavy on me too. I have no idea what comes next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that everyone who reads this during this crisis is safe, keeping fit, and eating well.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 04 Apr 2020 20:57:20 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://jetholt.com/repatriated/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jetholt.com/repatriated/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>4x4x48</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Last year, I listened to the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Living-SEAL-Training-Toughest-Planet-ebook/dp/B00U6DNZB2&quot;&gt;Living with a SEAL&lt;/a&gt; on Audible, where Jessie Itzler trained with David Goggins - the eponymous Navy SEAL - for a month, listing the workouts as they go. Whilst the book inspired me to work out harder and for longer, I never did any of the workouts. This weekend, David Goggins challenged his followers to complete one of the workouts mentioned in the book.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t read Living with a SEAL or don’t know who David Goggins is, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bklrNzdtU3Q&quot;&gt;watch some of Itzler’s stories about their month together&lt;/a&gt;. None of those stories come close to the insane feats that Goggins has achieved, but that’s besides the point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Itzler, the hardest challenge mentioned in the book was when Goggins wanted them both to run 48 miles in 48 hours, by running four miles every four hours. He called this challenge the 4x4x48. To train for this, they were both going to run 4.25 miles every 6 hours for 24 hours (aka 4.25 miles every 6 hours for a whole day).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I could tell from the book, Itzler didn’t finish his 4x4x48, though not for lack of trying - they achieved good times on very hilly terrain until he encountered problems. Jessie sprained his groin after the fourth run, meaning he only ran 16.1 miles. They substituted the remaining runs with pushups, and ended up doing 700. This is still a heroic effort, but it has to be said that he didn’t achieve what they had set out to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goggins is one of my idols, so when he &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/B9SQ4AxFnsX/&quot;&gt;challenged his followers&lt;/a&gt; to do the 4x4x48, I knew I had to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, for the week leading up to Goggins’ challenge, I had been enjoying a series of lumps swelling in the space where the leg joins the torso. It felt like I had a cluster of hot marbles stuck in my leg, and it was painful to the touch. I didn’t plan to take Goggins up on his challenge, naturally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The morning of the challenge, I went to see a doctor about the lumps and she told me that it was probably just my lymphatic system swelling for some reason, and that it would go away with time. It was probably just my body fighting off an infection. Naturally I worried that it might be Coronavirus, and I asked if I would be okay to do cardio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She said that it’d be okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, that’s it then, I realised. The challenge is on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, I believe that the area where I was experiencing the swelling is still referred to as my groin, so both Jessie and I had groinal issues whilst doing the 4x4x48.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, 48 hours is a long time, and 48 miles (77.25km) is a pretty far distance. It makes sense to prepare for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;food&quot;&gt;Food&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running 4 miles burns an estimated 600-700 calories for my body, according to my fitness apps. 48 miles therefore requires between 7200 and 8400 calories. Let’s call that 3900 per day. Taking into account my &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basal_metabolic_rate&quot;&gt;basal metabolic rate&lt;/a&gt;, which is somewhere around 2100 calories per day, I estimated that I needed to eat somewhere around 6000 calories for each 24 hours of the challenge, or 1000 calories between each run, if I was looking to maintain my current weight. I don’t mind being slightly under that threshold, as losing fat is still something I’m working towards, but being drastically under the threshold could cause problems. I could fail to complete the challenge, or perhaps even cause medical complications. It’s important to feed the machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eating wouldn’t be a huge problem during daylight hours - especially if I ate a big lunch before starting the challenge - as there are plenty of places to eat within a short walk of my hotel. It was the nights that I figured would be a problem. I’m not exactly a picky eater but I often find it hard to find somewhere that I’d be willing to eat, and the places I frequent all close at 10PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to stock up instead; buy a couple of boxes of cereals to eat; pick up a couple of portions of tofu tacos; and maybe some fruit and potato chips too. This meant that after the night runs - and perhaps at times when I felt too exhausted to go out - I’d be able to eat at my hotel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;drink&quot;&gt;Drink&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for hydration, I wasn’t too concerned. Whilst yes, I’m in Malaysia where even a short walk can make you sweat, I’d make sure to always bring a litre bottle with me. I guessed that I’d spend all of my daytime runs in the KLCC park, where there are chilled, filtered drinking water stations for if I got too thirsty. The remaining 4 runs would be at night when the park was closed, but it would also hopefully be a lot cooler meaning I’d sweat a whole lot less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for electrolytes, there’s a 24 hour 7/11 on the ground floor of my building, so I’d be able to easily buy sports drinks after each run. It just so happened that this challenge had good timing, as they were running a promotion on the brand I usually drink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;clothing&quot;&gt;Clothing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also thought briefly about my clothing situation. Whilst I used to have 4 pairs of everything, I only have 4 t-shirts, 3 pairs of running shorts, 2 pairs of underwear, and 3 pairs of socks now. The difference is because I’ve worn out much of my clothing recently and haven’t yet gone to replace them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 4 miles, I’d definitely be wet from sweat, and would need to rinse and clean the clothes I had worn. My clothes are made of a fast drying material, and from experience I knew it took somewhere around 8 hours or so for them to dry out to a satisfactory level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to reserve a pair of shorts and a tshirt for wearing between runs, as I didn’t want to risk having to wear damp clothes in my downtime. This left the situation looking pretty bleak, as by the time one piece has be drying for about 7 hours it’d be time to start wearing it again. I’d almost certainly be wearing damp clothes at some point during the event…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I thought of this sooner I’d have bought replacement clothes, but I didn’t, so that was that. Preparation over, I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;run-1&quot;&gt;Run 1&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Friday 6th March 2020, 16:00&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 4PM on Friday 6th March, I got dressed and laced up my running shoes, ready to begin the ordeal ahead. I was starting earlier than David Goggins by 20 hours, mostly because of a 16 hour time zone difference, though I had done the time zone conversion wrong at the time and thought I was starting just 12 hours ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wouldn’t usually consider running at 4PM in Malaysia. The few times I did that, I regretted it because I overheated rapidly and experienced sunburn on my neck. Thankfully for this first 4PM run, the sky was heavy with dark clouds and looked like it might rain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/4xclouds.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Storms above KL.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Storms above KL.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past month, I’ve been restricting myself to zone 2 heartrate (as measured by my Polar OH1), so it felt pretty good to run at a pace faster for once. A few enjoyable loops of the very hilly KLCC park later and I was clocking in at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/3158421433&quot;&gt;4 miles in just over 40 minutes&lt;/a&gt;. Strava helpfully chirped up with a message saying that this run ‘was harder than [my] usual effort’. You’re damned right! I felt great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked a stranger to take a photo of me. Whilst walking back to my hotel, it started raining almost right on cue to cool me down. I showered, taking the time to wring the sweat and rainwater out of my clothes, lather them in soap, rinse them, and wring them out again once more. This will be the first and last time I discuss showering. It’s boring and there aren’t many ways to write about it. Know that I showered after every run, and know that wringing my clothes out really ripped apart the skin of my hands by the end of the challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/4xp1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;After my first run.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;After my first run&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did stretches in my down time whilst I waited to begin the next run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;run-2&quot;&gt;Run 2&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Friday 6th March 2020, 20:00&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the 8PM run it was already dark. There seems to be a peak time between 6PM and 8PM in the evening when a hundred or so other people walk and run in the park. Come at any time before or after that during an evening, and you’ll feel like you’re running alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As before, it felt good to run at a harder pace than usual, but I began to feel a sharp pain just below my hip (I think the top of my IT band?) towards the end of the run. This has been a common occurrence since I arrived in Kuala Lumpur, and I can’t really explain it, though it might be something to do with the running surface in the park. A few times, the pain has left me struggling to walk properly the next day, so I’ve been substituting runs for the elliptical and stationary bike in an attempt to give myself time to heal between runs. I’m not going to be doing any substitutions this time, so I just have to suck it up. The show must go on, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/3158863871&quot;&gt;and I finish strong again in just over 41 minutes.&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/4xp2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;After my second run.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;After my second run.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I showered and rinsed my clothes, before going to pick up tacos from Mad Mex in KLCC Suria, as I had planned. I ate a portion and brought two portions home. I go there often enough that the staff know my order, so they were surprised when I ordered so much. Even if they didn’t know me, I think that they’d be surprised by such a big order. I explained what I was doing with the whole running event. They could hardly believe it, and they had to keep asking me questions to make sure they hadn’t misunderstood because of the language barrier. They wished me luck and told me they’d fill my tacos with extra vegetables and tofu rancheros free of charge. I picked up some pineapple chunks and some potato chips from the supermarket downstairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I called my girlfriend and helped her practice English for her upcoming IELTS test. Despite usually staying up later than this, I already felt very tired. I think it might have been some kind of ‘sympathy exhaustion’, with my mind feeling tired when it thought about the version of me at the end of the race. I was trying not to think about it, but my mind knew what was coming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;run-3-midnight&quot;&gt;Run 3, Midnight&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Saturday 7th March 2020, 00:00&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Midnight is accompanied with the closing of KLCC Park, so I wasn’t able to run there for this leg of the challenge. Instead, I left my hotel, picked a direction, and ran. When I reached approximately 2 miles, I turned back. It’s a simple system! Unintentionally, I ended up passing by Jalan Alor, a famous (and generally crowded) street food… uh.. street. I’ve been avoiding it on this trip to KL because of the Coronavirus, not that I’ve ever eaten there. It still seemed pretty busy, which worried me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/4xalor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jalan Alor, from afar.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Jalan Alor, from afar.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lap was just a little slower &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/3159416358&quot;&gt;than the pace of my previous two runs&lt;/a&gt; at 43:10. I don’t think I was running any slower, I think it was just that there were some delays whilst I had to wait for traffic lights when I needed to cross the roads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t know if it was okay to take naps as part of this challenge or not, so stayed awake. I’ve almost run a half marathon now, and it’s 1AM, so I’m tired. My eyes really didn’t want to stay open, though I was terrified that I might accidentally fall asleep and miss part of the challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to stimulate my brain by practising languages on Duolingo. I’m currently learning German, Indonesian, and Spanish. I’m not really any good at any of those, but I enjoy it a lot, and hopefully one day I will be. Whilst using that app, I inadvertently ate all of the potato chips and pineapple chunks that I had bought. I hadn’t been paying attention, and I didn’t get any “you’re getting full” warning from my body, presumably because I was still hungry from running. Eating those chips would turn out to be a huge mistake, as you’ll soon see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-4&quot;&gt;Part 4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Saturday 7th March 2020, 04:00&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I laced up and headed out without a plan for where to go. The hip pain that I had felt at the end of the second run was already coming back to haunt me, and it caused me trouble from the very first step. I ignored it, and the pain quickly went away when my body realised I didn’t care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst running, I saw several big trucks spraying water everywhere. I think that they were spraying things that people frequently interact with like bus stops, traffic crossings, and trash cans. They were using powerful pressure hoses, and I couldn’t help but wonder if it was related to the coronavirus, or if it was just part of the regular city maintenance. I had seen one truck spraying water at midnight too, but didn’t make any connection at that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/4xtruck.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Trucks spraying water&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Trucks spraying water.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around the mid-point of my run, I ended up running through a very lively area. Every street I had run through was dead up until this point, so I guess I hit KL’s pulsing nightlife artery. I’m not one to enjoy a city’s nightlife, and was shocked by how busy it still was at ~4:20AM. I saw lots of what I could only assume were prostitutes. They were ushering me towards them and trying to grab on to me. I have to wonder what they think the big runner guy that’s bounding down the road drenched in sweat would want with their services, but alas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third and fourth miles were really tough. I simply felt like I had no energy. My stomach was churning and I kept burping and farting. I realised that this was probably the 1000kcals of fat-loaded potato chips I had pigged out with earlier, and that my body was protesting that I gave it junk food at a time it needed high grade energy. I felt shame and regret.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/3159962815&quot;&gt;By the time I had finished this lap&lt;/a&gt; (in 44:33), Goggins had uploaded a now-deleted post to Instagram where he gave some tips to his followers for how to prepare for the race and how to get through it. He was due to start in 8 hours, and had some useful advice. He recommended that you only think about the next 4 miles and not the whole 48 mile. Just take them as they come, don’t worry about the future. That’s pretty good life advice!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We suffer more often in apprehension than reality.&lt;br /&gt;
– &lt;cite&gt;Seneca the Younger&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goggins recommended eating and drinking a lot, and that you should catch 1 hour to 30 minute naps where possible. I decided to take that advice, and cracked open the tacos that I had bought 8 or more hours earlier. By now, the soft corn shells had become hard at the edges, and had split completely down the middle. It was like holding a sandwich. There was a mildly funky smell to them, the filling had congealed, and the lettuce was not looking fresh. Oh well, it’s completely plant-based. What’s the worse that can happen?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I slept for an hour and a half.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-5&quot;&gt;Part 5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Saturday 7th March 2020, 08:00&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt dread before starting this run. Whilst moving between my bedroom and the bathroom, my legs felt completely shot and I was limping. None of my socks had dried, so I had the fun experience of trying to put on damp socks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By now, I’d already matched the furthest distance I had ever run in 1 day, so was now moving through new territory. I felt bloated from the chips and the tacos, and all around had a bad mentality going in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/4xlight.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Morning light.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Morning light.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, the run ended up being quite a slog. The park was open by now, which is nice because I don’t have to worry about traffic. It’s also a curse because the park is VERY hilly. I ended up feeling pretty terrible the whole way around; my chest felt tight, my heart felt like it was going crazy despite only being zone 2/3, and I kept burping and farting because my stomach was so unhappy with the potato chips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that all sounds terrible, and you’re thinking that I should have stopped, then yeah, it was terrible, and not stopping was exactly the point of the exercise for me. This experience is meant to suck. There’s no other reason to do it. It’s not a good way of training physically. It’s a good way of training mentally. It’s about making sure you keep going, even if you’re in a bad spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite how I was feeling, I soldiered on. The run ended up being &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/3170381800&quot;&gt;8 minutes slower than my first run&lt;/a&gt;, coming in at 48:48. This was partially because I ended up taking four 1-minute walking breaks to let my heart relax somewhat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The free breakfast at my hotel was lacklustre again, and the only thing I could eat was watermelon and toast. I ate what I would guess was almost a third of a watermelon. That probably wasn’t enough calories, so I tucked in to my second portion of tacos. The normally soft shells had a consistency like jerky, and the tofu/vegetable mix were even smellier than the last time. This wasn’t going to make my stomach feel any better. I definitely regretted eating those potato chips earlier. I should had eaten these instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lesson learned, don’t be weak. Don’t buy potato chips!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to sleep again but failed; my stomach was not doing well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-6&quot;&gt;Part 6&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Saturday 7th March 2020, 12:00&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By now, Goggins was starting the event, so I briefly watched his livestream before setting off. This afternoon was hot. Very, very hot. Worse still, it was bright. There were no storm to shelter me from the sun this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was so hot, that by the time I reached the park, my arm looked like this because of all of the sweat:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/4xsweat.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Arm sweat&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Arm sweat.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse was the fact that after I wiped the sweat away, it’d come back within 10 seconds. Every. Single. Time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I compensated for this scorching heat by taking many breaks along the way to try to keep cool. Initially, this just meant dropping my place for a minute or two, but later I also resorting to walking for a few stretches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The heat made the run feel unpleasant at the time, but I felt amazing once I was finished. Despite all the heat and breaks, I was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/3160640780&quot;&gt;faster than the previous run&lt;/a&gt; by 2 and a half minutes, coming in at 46:22, which goes to show how badly all that bloating can affect you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I slept for 2 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-7&quot;&gt;Part 7&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Saturday 7th March 2020, 16:00&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that last run was hot, this run was like going through Death Valley. Well, not really. Some incredible athletes actually run 135 miles through Death Valley during the peak of summer. David Goggins specifically got into ultrarunning just so that he could run that race. I’m not going to pretend my experience was anything like that, but it was still hot for me and I was far outside my comfort zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sun was so bright that I found myself running between patches of shade on the edges of the path. I’d veer from side to side, just to be in the shade for a few seconds longer. Drenched in sweat, and generally feeling fatigued, I passed the “Marathon” mark at just over half way through the leg. I’ve never ran a Marathon before, so this goes some way to showing me that I could do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of the run, I remembered that the park’s water fountains were chilled, and thought that they’d be the perfect thing to pour over myself. It took a long time to fill my water bottle up, but it felt so refreshing once the liquid hit my face. It washed the sweat from my brow down across my face, and my eyes started stinging from the salts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All told, if the heat had slowed me down, it didn’t slow me any more than the self-inflicted bloating had slowed my 5th run. I &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/3160930715&quot;&gt;finished in 48:38&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/4xp7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;After my seventh run.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;After my seventh run.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ate lunch at the mall and had a 30 minute cat nap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-8&quot;&gt;Part 8&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Saturday 7th March 2020, 20:00&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I woke up again in preparation to run this leg, I felt like I was trapped in a loop. My life felt like it had become a cycle of getting up and running that wasn’t going to end. I felt like David Goggins was torturing me, and me in particular. It’s easy to have hyperbole like that in a story like this, but it actually, genuinely felt like that. Some combination of factors from this experience came together to make it so that I honestly believed that David Goggins was punishing me, and me in particular, like some kind of weird lucid not-quite-hallucination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also limping again, but badly this time. I was struggling to bend my right knee. Luckily, I had woken up with plenty of time to stretch, which helped greatly, but my knee still hurt with every step of the first mile before eventually fading to a light twinge. The bloat was back with a vengeance, and I was burping and farting repeatedly. It wasn’t too hot, so the heat wasn’t slowing me down, but it sill wasn’t a good run. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/3161790572&quot;&gt;The pain and exhaustion slowed me, coming in at 47:10.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it was night time again, I had intended to call my girlfriend to help her practice English for her upcoming test, but I was too exhausted. Sorry, BRO!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I slept again, but I’m not sure for how long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-9&quot;&gt;Part 9&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sunday 8th March 2020, 00:00&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funnily enough, my girlfriend thought I had already finished the exercise when I told her I was awake at 23:35. When I told her I still needed to run, she thought that this had to be my last one. I wish, I still have to run 16 miles…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As before, the park is closed at midnight. I decided to copy my route from last night, as it was simple and fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure if I need to keep saying this - it should be obvious by now - but this was a horrible run, and I felt terrible. That’s the point of this exercise though, so I guess it was going really well; I haven’t given up yet! Despite being cool outside, I was still overheating a lot, and I started to feel like I wanted to vomit, but not in such a way that I believed I actually would. I took a few ‘slow jog’ breaks and one ‘walk break’ to get through it. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/3162701375&quot;&gt;49:50&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/4xp9.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;After my ninth run.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;After my ninth run.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A highlight of the run would be when a big seed - or perhaps a small apple - fell from a tree and hit me in the head. Fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rested and stretched, but I wasn’t able to get to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-10&quot;&gt;Part 10&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sunday 8th March 2020, 04:00&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the worst run of the event, by a large margin! I decided to head north after leaving my hotel, which meant I would be passing through areas that I had only seen a few times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That made for a very nice sightseeing tour, but it didn’t do anything to help the fatigue. Well, that’s not exactly true, as it was generally quite flat. I felt light-headed and very weak for much of the last two miles, and I had to walk for minutes at a time just to get through things. I tried to continue jogging where I was able. I might feel terrible, but I’m not going to quit. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/3163323845&quot;&gt;56:45&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent most of the night eating cereal and chatting to my relatives. I figured that part of the reason I struggled so much during this leg might be electrolytes, so made sure to drink a whole litre of sports drink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 6AM I realised that I had to run again in 2 hours, and was filled with dread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trapped in a loop!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-11&quot;&gt;Part 11&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sunday 8th March 2020, 08:00&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8 AM meant I was back in KLCC park. That should have be nice, but I was not looking forward to those hills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The run ended up being extremely difficult. One of the only things that got me through it was an internal mantra that went something like “Come on Jet, it’ll end. And after this, you have just 4 more miles. That’s nothing! Come on!!”. My spirit was definitely there, but my body was struggling to keep up. On the many hills, my heart felt like it was going to burst out of my chest. My heartrate monitor was still only observing Zone 2 (~130bpm). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/3163750741&quot;&gt;This run finished at 58:55, the slowest time of the event.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hotel was serving breakfast by the time I finished, so I ate a big heaped bowl of baked beans and a dozen or more slices of watermelon. I drank 500ml of electrolyte drink, and felt refreshed, and for once, not bloated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to overstate how exhausted I was by this point. The day was actually my anniversary with my girlfriend. We’re not often in the same physical location, so I wished her a happy anniversary by video message in the morning. I watched those videos back whilst editing this post, and was struck by the fact that it looked like I didn’t know how to speak English. Lots of long pauses at odd intervals and sentences that went nowhere. I looked exhausted. Exhausted!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rested for an hour and a half, but didn’t manage to sleep for some reason. That’s definitely a pattern for this challenge for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-12&quot;&gt;Part 12&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sunday 8th March 2020, 12:00&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the last run! It was noon again, so obviously it was going to be incredibly hot. I knew that going in, so made sure to drink a litre before heading out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowing that this would be the last run gave me a small second wind, and I found myself able to power through and finish strong. Well, not exactly strong, but I felt much stronger than the few more recent runs. I finished in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/3170423653&quot;&gt;just under 52 minutes&lt;/a&gt;. This last leg was 7 minutes faster than the slowest run, and 11.5 minutes slower than the fastest (which was also the first run).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/4xp12.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;After my last run.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;After my last run.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was pretty chuffed to be finished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;roundup&quot;&gt;Roundup&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, this was a very fun challenge and something I’d love to do again. Ideally at long but specific intervals, let’s say every six months to a year or so. I’d love to use it to track the change in my fitness and conditioning. Ideally, next time I’d love to be able to do the whole thing without slowing my pace or walking. I’d also love to see if I can get through it without bloating just by eating smarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nice thing about the challenge is that it breaks a huge distance into small, manageable chunks. That’s often a suggestion that successful people make to achieving anything in life; if you need to do something, what’s the smallest chunk you can do now? Enough chunks, and eventually the task will be completed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I tried to run 48 miles in two days naturally, perhaps 24 on one day, and another 24 on the next, I’d probably (definitely?) fail, but by splitting it like this, I was able to keep going because I only had to focus on a 4 mile chunk at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But yes, before this challenge, the furthest that I had run in one go is the 15 miles (24.2km) that I ran for &lt;a href=&quot;/run-till-you-drop/&quot;&gt;Run Till You Drop&lt;/a&gt;. Whilst not consecutive, I now know that I am capable of running up to 48 miles!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s some stats to round things off:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;48 miles ran (77.25km)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;48 hours elapsed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;12 showers taken&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;7.5 hours (+/- 1 hour) of sleep&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;8 blisters developed
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;6 Foot Blisters&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 Hand Blisters (from wringing water out of clothes)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2020 03:05:23 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://jetholt.com/4x4x48/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jetholt.com/4x4x48/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Extract Wav File Data for Code</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Back in 2018, I developed Seismograf, a Eurorack module that outputs drum samples. I wanted a way of quickly trying out different samples, so &lt;a href=&quot;/seismograf/#wav-manipulation&quot;&gt;wrote a python script that would automate the processing and conversion of WAV files for me&lt;/a&gt;, outputting the samples in a format that I could easily paste into code. I didn’t plan on sharing that script, but I recently saw someone trying to do the same thing on Facebook and figured it might be worth sharing my script.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Seismograf, I needed 10 bit samples that would fit neatly into ‘power of two’ length blocks like 1024 words or 2048 words (where a word was 14 bits long).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to be able to trial many different samples quickly, so I really didn’t want to have to waste time in a sound processing program manually trimming away silence, or amplifying the sound, or downsampling to 10 bit, or whatever. That would be really time consuming, so I tried to automate those tasks and wrote a python script to do it all for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It outputs a txt file containing comma-separated decimal-representations of the wav file in a specified resolution and with a specified number of steps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw a synth DIY’er wanting to do similar on Facebook (actually I was tagged in the post), so figured I’d share this script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;use-the-script&quot;&gt;Use The Script&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/Jetroid/e1f8c3234d9831b90fd19d8aadb609a1&quot;&gt;Get the script here&lt;/a&gt;, or download it with wget:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;wget https://gist.githubusercontent.com/Jetroid/e1f8c3234d9831b90fd19d8aadb609a1/raw/626a671e847cbadfa397614014b3dbee68adc432/waveread.py
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, install python’s &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;wave&lt;/code&gt; library:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;pip install wave
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then you can execute the program like this (make sure you’re using python 3):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;python waveread.py /path/to/sound.wav r s
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;r&lt;/code&gt; represents the resolution in bits, and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;s&lt;/code&gt; represents the number of samples in bits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for example, to process the file &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bassdrum.wav&lt;/code&gt;, and output 4096 samples (4096 = 2^12) that have 10 bit resolution, run the script like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;python waveread.py ./bassdrum.wav 10 12
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-this-script-does&quot;&gt;What this script does&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You provide it with three parameters: the filename; the resolution in bits; and the number of steps in bits (ie 11 bit steps = 2048 total samples outputted)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The script then&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Opens the wav file you give it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attempts to find the start and end of the sample, then crops away any silence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rescales the audio so that the loudest (highest amplitude) part of the sample is equal to the highest/lowest possible value for your given resolution. (ie: All wav files processed will have the same ‘loudness’)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Determines the ratio &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;n&lt;/code&gt; between the number of samples needed and the number of samples available. Example: if the cropped wav file has 8192 samples, and we want to output 2048 samples, then the ratio &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;n = 4.0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Selects every &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;n&lt;/code&gt;th sample from the cropped wav. Therefore we get the correct number of samples.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Writes all of the new samples to a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.txt&lt;/code&gt; file with the same name as wav file, in the same directory as the wav file. The data is represented as decimals. Each sample is separated by a comma. For ease of viewing, a line break has been inserted every 16 samples.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-this-script-does-not-do&quot;&gt;What this script does not do&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Losslessly recreate the sample. By definition, some data is lost to A) downsampling to the correct resolution. B) downsampling to the correct number of steps.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It doesn’t have an option to output every sample in a wav file / output non-power-of-two numbers of samples. Sorry, but I wrote this for my needs and I needed specific numbers of samples. The script will probably be&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Correct the centerline / silence line / zero line. (I’m not sure what to call this). If your sample has ‘zero’ (silence) as a value above or below that, this script will not correct that, and may manipulate the sample incorrectly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;please-credit&quot;&gt;Please credit&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you use this script for anything other than personal use, please credit myself (Jet Holt) and Frequency Central.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://jetholt.com&quot;&gt;Jet Holt&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://frequencycentral.co.uk&quot;&gt;Frequency Central&lt;/a&gt; for waveread.py.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Include hyperlinks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://jetholt.com&quot;&gt;jetholt.com&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://frequencycentral.co.uk&quot;&gt;frequencycentral.co.uk&lt;/a&gt; where possible.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2020 04:58:10 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://jetholt.com/wav-files/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jetholt.com/wav-files/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Neograf</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Neograf is a Pitch/Gate sequencer based on our &lt;a href=&quot;/polygraf/&quot;&gt;Polygraf&lt;/a&gt; drum sequencer design. Intended to be programmed using a keyboard, Neograf has a simple and intuitive feature set. It’s something I’ve always wanted to make - or at least, since I’ve been working on synth projects - and I feel that it really rounds out the -graf family of modules that we’ve been developing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neograf is what Polygraf would be if it had been designed to output pitch and gate. The elevator pitch for Neograf would look something like this: “Polygraf is a cool sequencer for Drum Modules. So what would it look like if we made a variant for controlling synth voices? Well, it’d probably have a very similar interface to Polygraf, right? And perhaps it’d be the most natural to program it by playing keys on a keyboard. Oh, and it’s very important that we be able to be able to have rests and legato somehow. Most tunes are longer than 16 step, so it’d be nice if we could very easily and intuitively switch between playing 16, 32, or 64 note sequences.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The true origin of Neograf relates to being very sick, the tetris theme, and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3gZC5763wYk&quot;&gt;YouTube keyboard&lt;/a&gt;. I won’t elaborate further as it’s a confusing story, but there we go. I’ll leave it to your imagination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, Neograf used Polygraf’s code as a base. I even tried making a kludge-y insert to replace the PIC in a production model of Polygraf so that I didn’t have to make too much hardware, but it ended up being too unstable to use so I quickly abandoned it. That was fine though, as our hardware ended up being very different from the hardware of Polygraf - only the seven segment display remained as a commonality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/neograf-kludge.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;An early attempt to convert a Polygraf into a Neograf.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;An early attempt to convert a Polygraf into a Neograf.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I decided to adapt the old Polygraf prototype. That made me laugh, as the whole thing is a parallel of what happened with &lt;a href=&quot;/chronograf/&quot;&gt;Chronograf&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/seismograf/&quot;&gt;Seismograf&lt;/a&gt; - Seismograf was a specialised version of Chronograf, and we re-used the prototype there too. It was pretty funny to be using the old Polygraf prototype again after so long. The hardware changes ended up being numerous, so it quickly turned into a spaghetti mess of wires as I made hardware additions or circuit re-routes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;development-process&quot;&gt;Development Process&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neograf was fairly simple to develop as I was able to build on top of Polygraf rather than starting from scratch. I was also able to borrow code and designs from Little Melody for outputting a quantised note.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started programming Neograf by focusing on getting the output section working. It’s the simplest part to test, as I could just hardcode a sequence into the EEPROM memory and tweak playback until it was reproduced properly. I came up with my own musical notation language that was able to represent notes, gates, rests, and legato, and transcribed the Tetris theme into it. I then wrote a python script that would convert my notation into the bytes that I wanted to store in my EEPROM data. The python script ended up being very useful. It was a real pain to manually transcribe the beats for Polygraf into the EEPROM - here I could just use my notation and copy/paste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After playback was confirmed working, I plugged our Waldorf KB37 eurorack keyboard into the Neograf prototype and made the changes necessary Polygraf’s record code. Very quickly I ended up with something that could record and playback notes. Neat!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We quickly noticed that before we recorded a sequence into Neograf, we’d want to actually play it by hand a few times first. With Neograf between the keyboard and the synthesiser, this wasn’t so easy - we either had to unpatch Neograf or use a different keyboard. We figured that a musician wouldn’t want to have to have unpatch Neograf every time that they wanted to play their keyboard, so we introduced an ‘Audition’ mode where Neograf just repeats it’s input on it’s output. It isn’t a perfect reproduction as Neograf can only output 5 octaves (and outputs as a quantised note), but it’s good enough for our purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next thing that was painfully obvious was that we needed a way for Neograf to play longer sequences. The tetris theme that I had transcribed spanned two sequences, and it was a real pain to have to mess with the pattern knob every time we wanted to play the full thing. We decided to implement a switch that allowed Neograf to play just 1 sequence, or 2 or 4 consecutive ones. This worked really nicely. It was such a good feature that &lt;a href=&quot;/polygraf/#sequence-chaining&quot;&gt;we went back to Polygraf and figured out a way to implement it there, too&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/neograf-prototype.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Neograf prototype, adapted from the Polygraf prototype. What a tangled mess of wires!&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The Neograf prototype, adapted from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/polygraf-prototype.jpg&quot;&gt;Polygraf prototype&lt;/a&gt;. What a tangled mess of wires! The smaller board is a common 1v/Octave PWM conditioner that we used for Neograf, &lt;a href=&quot;/quash/&quot;&gt;QuaSH&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;/little-melody/&quot;&gt;Little Melody&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point we noticed that we were only using the “State” input (used to input sequences without a keyboard in the same style as Polygraf) in Play mode, and decided to give it a second purpose in Play mode - make it work for adding Bias. Obviously, it would be annoying to have a Bias applied just because the “State” input was in a certain position when you turned the module on (or switched between Record and Play mode), so we only add Bias when the “State” input changes during playback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not a musician and so I haven’t been exposed to many other sequencers and other music tech before. When I’m designing for Frequency Central, some of my assumptions about how something should be implemented are sometimes incorrect. Fortunately, I’m not building these modules in a vacuum, and my father - himself a veteran musician - frequently corrects the design. A glaring instance of this happening was that I initially implemented the ‘gate’ output for Neograf in the style of the &lt;a href=&quot;/polygraf/#pre-programmed-patterns&quot;&gt;‘Triggates’ mode that I designed for Polygraf&lt;/a&gt;. It worked fine for many cases, but it turned out to be the wrong thing to do. It limited the possibilities that you can make with your tune. I ended up changing this completely, and instead implemented a ‘gate length’ input that allows the user to vary their gate duration between 10ms and 150ms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gate length was the final feature to be implemented, and whilst doing so, I encountered a very confusing issue where programming the PICs seemed to make them unreadable. I was really stumped by this, and didn’t know what to do nor how to proceed for a few weeks. I was really hesitant to do anything as every time I burned - and subsequently killed - a PIC, it I felt like I was just throwing money away. I was so confused that I even &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microchip.com/forums/m1121166.aspx&quot;&gt;consulted the smart folks over at the Microchip forum&lt;/a&gt;. As expected, they knew exactly what to do, and the problem turned out to be an undocumented hardware bug with older PICs like the one I was using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a side note, when I work on a PIC project with Frequency Central, the non-PIC circuit is usually fairly simple as the code does most of the heavy lifting. If there’s a way to make the PIC do something, we usually try to do it, as that makes the most economical sense. With Neograf, a lot of complicated switching is done in the analogue domain, so the electronics are actually quite complicated here. This switching was needed because we decided to multiplex the inputs of the PIC to do different functions depending on if we are in Play, Audition, or Record mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like Neograf; it feels like it fills a gap missing from the -graf series of modules. Whilst Cryptograf is great as an analogue sequencer (especially when paired with Polygraf), it’s more of an ‘in the moment, happy accident’ tool. Neograf fills the hole of wanting to make reproducible patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used it to record and play back the melody from one of my favourite songs, &lt;em&gt;Feels Like We Only Go Backwards&lt;/em&gt; by Tame Impala:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet tw-align-center&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-dnt=&quot;true&quot; data-theme=&quot;dark&quot; data-link-color=&quot;#d05d5d&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;It&amp;#39;s so cool to play a melody from one of your favourite songs (&lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/xvIR5Bpg25&quot;&gt;https://t.co/xvIR5Bpg25&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/tameimpala?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@tameimpala&lt;/a&gt;) on a sequencer you designed yourself! 😍 &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/b6j60LfW43&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/b6j60LfW43&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jet Holt (@JetroidMakes) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/JetroidMakes/status/1203491603484151808?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;December 8, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time this article was written, Neograf only exists as a rough prototype, so watch this space for more development, and information when we release it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/neograf-visualisation.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Neograf panel visualisation.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Neograf panel visualisation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2019 07:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://jetholt.com/neograf/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jetholt.com/neograf/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>QuaSH</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Back in 2013/4, whilst developing the &lt;a href=&quot;/bartos-flur/&quot;&gt;Bartos Flur&lt;/a&gt; for my A-Level Electronics Project, I developed a very simple PIC program that worked as a chromatic quantiser. We nicknamed it ‘QuaSH’, though we didn’t actually have a use for it. Whilst developing &lt;a href=&quot;/little-melody/&quot;&gt;Little Melody&lt;/a&gt;, we had need of a quantiser again, and so I reviewed and reused my old code. One thing lead to another, and we decided to expand Little Melody’s quantiser into it’s own full module, too.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;QuaSH grew out of two things: A throwaway idea we made for &lt;a href=&quot;/bartos-flur/&quot;&gt;Bartos Flur&lt;/a&gt; purely to meet my academic requirements, and a feature we were developing for &lt;a href=&quot;/little-melody/&quot;&gt;Little Melody&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;from-little-melody-to-quash&quot;&gt;From Little Melody to QuaSH&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make Little Melody simpler to use, we realised that we needed a quantiser. I looked back to my old code from 2014, and whilst I liked the implementation concept, I decided to rewrite the code as the actual implementation was flawed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quantiser that I had designed is fairly novel in it’s technical implementation. To be able to output a 5 octave range, you need to be able to output 61 distinct values at specific levels. Unfortunately, when you’re working with very low bit numbers (like may be found on a cheap PWM unit or DAC unit), this means that you’d have error where the outputted value doesn’t correctly line up with the required value, meaning the note feels out of tune.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To illustrate the problem, imagine we were using a 6-bit DAC. Let’s cherry pick the example of the 50th value in our range - the D from the fifth octave - which requires us to output 4.166 volts. The closest that a 6 bit DAC can output would be either 4.206 volts, or 4.126 volts. Both possible values are 0.040 volts incorrect. The difference between two distinct notes is just 0.081 volts, so both possible values are roughly ~50% wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a higher precision DAC can mitigate the issue, but this is often expensive. Martin Doudoroff measures this problem in various modules with his ‘nominal accuracy’ field in &lt;a href=&quot;https://doudoroff.com/quantizers/&quot;&gt;this comparison table&lt;/a&gt;. It’s an important issue!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/quash-prototype.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;QuaSH prototype.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;QuaSH prototype.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My implementation attempts to sidestep the DAC precision issue by outputting in the lower 61 values of the 64 value range. (ie representing a value that “should be” 5 volts as 4.84 volts) and then using amplifiers with a tiny gain to ‘correct’ the value to the correct range. By doing this, the DAC doesn’t ever have to try to output ‘in between values’ - it’s always outputting an exact, correct value. Our method has the downside that it uses additional hardware and that the amplifier needs to be trimmed to the correct gain, but it’s a solution that I liked and I decided to stick with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we had the quantiser built for Little Melody, we threw around the idea of using that chromatic quantisation functionality as it’s own standalone module. I realised that we had a spare input pin on the Little Melody PIC that we weren’t planning on using, and had the idea that we could use it to change what the function of the inputs and outputs of the PIC do. The pin would be used to determine which program the PIC should execute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quantiser doesn’t need any of the Little Melody specific features like division selections or modes, it needs scale and chord selections. It has totally different input and output requirements. Essentially, the idea would be: Plug the chip into the Little Melody hardware and it runs the same code as always, but if you plug it into QuaSH hardware, it runs completely different code to function as a quantiser. We could have achieved the same thing with two completely different programs on two different chips, but the advantage of this is that we only need to stock one PIC part, meaning the project is less of a risk/investment for Frequency Central.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/quash-production.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;QuaSH production model.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;QuaSH production model.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;coding-issues&quot;&gt;Coding Issues&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Development of QuaSH turned out to be pretty tricky because of our ‘two programs on one chip’ concept. I found that changing a section of code to implement a feature for QuaSH sometimes broke Little Melody in some way. I had to test both modules every time I made a change to either, which was slow and cumbersome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In hindsight, I went about implementing this ‘two programs on one chip’ idea the wrong way. It would have been better to keep the code for QuaSH and Little Melody completely separate. The two programs should never execute the same piece of code if it’s possible to avoid it. Unfortunately, due to the way the ideas evolved, that wasn’t what I did in practice. Originally, the QuaSH quantiser was only subtly different from the Little Melody quantiser and it made sense to reuse the code. As our requirements developed, the two programs became radically different. I ended up having little snippets of code everywhere saying “If Little Melody Do X, If QuaSH do Y”. It became a mess and I wish I had done things differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were times when the ‘two programs on one chip’ concept didn’t look like it could even be used. At one point I had issues with the PIC turning on and running the code for the wrong module, which was very frustrating to solve and filled me with feelings of dread. I tried various methods to correct course if the PIC accidentally became the wrong module, but in the end the simplest and most reliable solution seemed to be “wait a few seconds before deciding which module to be”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As both programs grew, I eventually reached the point where the total length of the code surpassed 2048 instructions. This meant that my code crossed a page boundary and due to a limitation in the PIC hardware, the program counter can’t uniquely identify each instruction any more. Attempts to access the program instruction at location 2049 will give you instruction 1, 2050 gives you 2, etc. You have to take special measures to keep the program working correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was my first time encountering this issue, and I didn’t notice the warning in my console (“Message[306] :  Crossing page boundary – ensure page bits are set.”). The console goes by so fast, and is packed with messages about things I have already addressed. I often don’t pay too much attention to it. As a result, I was completely perplexed as to why my code wasn’t working. Making changes to try to fix a broken feature caused another to break seemingly at random - my changes were pushing more and more code into the ‘inaccessible zone’ that the program counter couldn’t reach. Once I figured out what was going on, it was easy to fix the problem. I moved a big chunk of code to the second code page and added &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pagesel&lt;/code&gt; commands before the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;goto&lt;/code&gt; instructions that took me there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;quash-features&quot;&gt;QuaSH features&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;QuaSH ended up with quite a respectable feature set, in my opinion. It quantises to one of 16 scales or 8 chords and can output across 5 octave. You can use the offset input to change the pattern subtly, either by adding voltage as a bias, or by using it to set the key of the scales and chords - or both! Sampling only happens when you want it to, as we included a gate input and a switch to select between sampling always, only when the gate is high, or only on the rising edge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A feature we added very close to the end of development was the ability to turn the quantiser off and just use the module as a ‘pure’ sample and hold. When in ‘sample on rising edge’ mode, it acts like a classic sample and hold, whilst when it’s in ‘sample whilst gate high’ mode it acts a bit like a ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=w2DKgZHcmiU&quot;&gt;mute&lt;/a&gt;’. When in ‘always sample’ mode, the module is essentially bypassed. The feature is a bit lo-fi as our output from the PIC isn’t a great resolution, but it’s an option for people to make use of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/quash-mu-panel.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;QuaSH MU module panel.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;QuaSH MU module panel.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;QuaSH ended up being a really fun module. It’s one of the first Eurorack modules that I’ve had fun playing with on my own. It’s so simple to create something that sounds good - it doesn’t require musical knowledge or intuition at all. It’s innately musical because it quantises to known scales and chords, so even a non-musician like myself can use it to create something that sounds good. When I use it, it reminds me of Portal 2’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/mn1SPGTygIE&quot;&gt;Robot Waiting Room&lt;/a&gt;, and it brings me a lot of joy to understand how I could make music like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A demo of using QuaSH with a simple triangle LFO is below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet tw-align-center&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-dnt=&quot;true&quot; data-theme=&quot;dark&quot; data-link-color=&quot;#d05d5d&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Another project all finished up! 🎛&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Quantised Sample &amp;amp; Hold circuit, using a PIC16F88 programmed in Assembly. 👨‍💻&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Converts continuous signals into scales and chords. 🎧 &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/p2P2xqhTcr&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/p2P2xqhTcr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jet Holt (@JetroidMakes) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/JetroidMakes/status/1184597258614071298?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;October 16, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time this article was written, QuaSH already has a Eurorack prototype, and plans for a MU module are on the way too. Watch this space for more development, and information when we release it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2019 07:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://jetholt.com/quash/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jetholt.com/quash/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Little Melody</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Little Melody is a pseudo-sequencer pseudo-melodic-pattern-generator that I coded during Summer 2019. It’s frankly addictive-to-use for a musician, and you can get jamming in no time. It uses a clock divider, voltage mixer, and quantiser to make incredibly satisfying melodies. This article tells the story of how we came up with it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Way back in 2013 when Frequency Central designed &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.archive.org/web/20190515165654/http://www.frequencycentral.co.uk/?page_id=1694&quot;&gt;Pocket Calculator&lt;/a&gt; - a now-discontinued clock-divider module - we conceived of Little Melody. It would be an addon module that connected to Pocket Calculator’s ‘Expansion’ header, and would use the clock divisions to create a melody. We didn’t end up going with that design, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/eSBybJGZoCU?t=112&quot;&gt;the name&lt;/a&gt; and idea stuck around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Actually, the idea is much, much older than this, as it’s something my dad once wanted to build back when he was making his first modular synthesizers as a younger man. For me, there’s something very cool about working on a project that your father conceived of before you were even conceived.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theorised ‘Little Melody for Pocket Calculator’ would essentially allow you to assign voltages (which represent notes) to the different clock divisions, which were then mixed together. When that clock division is high, the note plays. When multiple divisions are high, the sum of the two would play (resulting in a higher pitched note), etc. The flaw/drawback with that idea was that the divisions for Pocket Calculator are static. Without changing the notes, it would have just played the same sequence over and over again. The only change that you would be able to make to the pattern is changing the set of notes that play. There just wouldn’t be much flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The version that we designed in 2019 aims to address these issues. Instead of having specific clock divisions on specific outputs like with Pocket Calculator, our new version has a ‘division selector’ potentiometer input for each output that allows you to change clock divisions on the fly. To simplify things, we reduced the total number of ‘outputs’ from the clock divider from 7 to 4. This version would essentially have a full Pocket Calculator hidden inside, and the user changes the routing of which division goes to which output. This new design means that you can keep the set of notes the same, but vary the order that they are played in the sequence, which adds a lot of variability and flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the idea in hand, it was time to start work…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;first-steps&quot;&gt;First Steps&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/pic-breakout.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;PIC breakout board, with bundled wires.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;PIC breakout board, with bundled wires.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have this PIC breakout board that I designed a few years ago. It has a series of commonly used components, inputs, and outputs that can be connected to a PIC in any configuration. I use it like a more-permanent breadboard; I make an approximation of the circuit I need, and then I use it to test inputs and outputs. Once I commit myself to a pinout for my PIC, I create a true prototype testing board that I develop the rest of the project with. I used this my breakout board for Little Melody to test the PIC’s interrupt-on-change module, which I intended to use for the Clock and Reset inputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had never used the interrupt-on-change module before, so it made sense to get that working correctly first. I hooked it up as a clock input that causes a bank of LEDs to count up in binary, and a reset input that turns all of the LEDs off. This was good as it meant that I had already implemented the clock counter that would serve as the core of the module. I like to make the most essential nugget of a PIC project first, so that I have a known-working baseline functionality to build upon. I’ve found that if I try to build too much at once, things go wrong for me. Since learning this, I try to build something small that I can test first, even if it’s something I know that I’ll have to mostly change it later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recording of this initial piece of code in action is demonstrated below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;youtube&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LMtqQVfcmxs&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;feature-innovations&quot;&gt;Feature Innovations&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst the bulk of the project had already been conceived years in advance of us actually developing the module, there was still room to create new features to enhance the possibilities. Whilst implementing the base feature set, we came up with a number of features that would enhance the flexibility of the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, we realised that we could have more than just a single ‘division selector’ that determined the routing for an output, but that we could include an additional ‘division presets selector’ that overrides the four individual selectors and changes them all. The user can then use the individual selectors to adapt the preset to their liking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/little-melody-prototype.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Little Melody prototype.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Little Melody prototype. The smaller board is a common 1v/Octave PWM conditioner that we used for Little Melody, &lt;a href=&quot;/quash/&quot;&gt;QuaSH&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;/neograf/&quot;&gt;Neograf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another feature we came up with is the idea of a ‘Modes’ input. The first two are very easy to explain. In the first mode, the internal clock divider simply counts up as normal - the same functionality as Pocket Calculator. In the second mode, the internal clock divider counts down (The outputs all start ‘on’). The remaining six modes are where things get complicated. These are ‘up/down modes’, and have specific clock division cutoff points. We’ll consider “Up/Down 16”, which is the up/down mode where the cutoff is at the /16 division. In this mode, for the first 16 clocks, we appear to be counting up normally. However, when the /16 output comes on, any clock outputs with clock divisions /1, /2, /4, and /8 start counting down. The remaining outputs continue to count up. After the 32nd clock, those /1, /2, /4, and /8 revert to counting up again. This is hard to imagine, but it has the effect that (depending on which divisions you have set) your pattern begins to sound a bit ‘triangular’, ‘sawtooth-like’, or ‘flip-floppy’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is represented in the graphic below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/little-melody-graphs.png&quot; alt=&quot;Different modes with different division settings.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Different modes with different division settings. X axis represents the number of clocks, Y axis represents the pitch.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We played with the module a lot after we had all of those features implemented correctly. (Implementation was surprisingly tricky, actually, and I had to write pseudocode in Python first to test the logic as the interplay between features makes things more complicated than it seems). The module felt good, really good. However, every time we wanted to change the notes in our sequence, we’d spend a bunch of time trying to tune individual voltages to be specific notes, as otherwise it’d be out of tune. This flicked a switch in my brain, and made me think of &lt;a href=&quot;/bartos-flur/#a-level-electronics&quot;&gt;the quantiser that I designed for my A-Level electronics project&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we included a quantiser right before the output, we’d remove the necessity for tuning the notes. It’ll take whatever imprecise voltages we throw at it and force it to be an exact, musical note. This last little feature brought everything together, and the module feels so user friendly because of it. It’s very simple to create something that sounds good. &lt;a href=&quot;/quash/&quot;&gt;We liked the quantiser feature a lot, and decided to spin the quantiser into it’s own module, too&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing this all together, our block diagram looked something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/little-melody-block-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Little Melody Block Diagram.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Little Melody Block Diagram.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final product - or the prototype of it, anyway - is incredibly fun to use. We found that if we just set the sliders (regular potentiometers on our prototype) to a few specific notes, that we would have a lot of fun to just start jamming with the division selectors. We periodically used the preset knob to select a base configuration to switch things up, and then varied the beat on that even more with the division selectors. Because we kept the sliders to the same position, our pattern had a fixed set of possible note - though they played in a varied order - and this lead to the changes in the pattern feeling like natural, intentional shifts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A demo of Little Melody is below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet tw-align-center&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-dnt=&quot;true&quot; data-theme=&quot;dark&quot; data-link-color=&quot;#d05d5d&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Some funky jams. 🎶 Damn, this thing is addictive. 💉 Just three modules in this tune!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Melodic Generator that uses clock divisions and CV mixing to make sick beats. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/2ZHshhV5ls&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/2ZHshhV5ls&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jet Holt (@JetroidMakes) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/JetroidMakes/status/1203838672308707328?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;December 9, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time this article was written, Little Melody only exists as a rough prototype, so watch this space for more development, and information when we release it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re also creating a variation of Little Melody - we’re calling it ‘High Towers’ - that acts as a pure clock divider, but keeping the innovative divider selections and modes. High Towers has an additional feature not found in Little Melody, where instead of outputting clock divisions, the module outputs a trigger after counting to the number specified by the divider’s value - ie, a divider set to /8 triggers every 8th pulse. The trigger can be offset by changing the mode, so that it can trigger every 7th pulse in the set of 8, or every 6th pulse in the set of 8, etc. Should be interesting!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/little-melody-visualisation.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Little Melody and High Towers panel visualisations.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Little Melody and High Towers panel visualisations.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2019 07:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://jetholt.com/little-melody/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jetholt.com/little-melody/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New Frequency Central Website</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For years, Frequency Central has been represented online with a very out-of-date website that just listed information about products with no way to purchase them. My main project for the summer of 2019 would be to implement a new, up-to-date website with current images, data, and descriptions that allowed customers to buy directly from us easily.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.archive.org/web/20190518035405/http://frequencycentral.co.uk/&quot;&gt;old Frequency Central website&lt;/a&gt; was incredibly outdated. It was also cumbersome to update because a products’ information had to be entered by hand across multiple pages. Take Waverunner for instance - if we wanted to change the graphic or text of Waverunner, we’d have to change it on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.archive.org/web/20190519093158/http://www.frequencycentral.co.uk/?page_id=416&quot;&gt;EU Synth DIY&lt;/a&gt; page, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.archive.org/web/20190519093203/http://www.frequencycentral.co.uk/?page_id=554&quot;&gt;EU Synth&lt;/a&gt; page, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.archive.org/web/20190519092919/http://www.frequencycentral.co.uk/?page_id=1285&quot;&gt;Waverunner DIY&lt;/a&gt; page, and the regular &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.archive.org/web/20190519092913/http://www.frequencycentral.co.uk/?page_id=1283&quot;&gt;Waverunner&lt;/a&gt; page. That’s a lot of effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering that a recent shift that had occurred within Frequency Central is the transition from silver panels to black panels, and we were looking at having to change hundreds of pictures on hundreds of pages. It was just untenable. It got to the point where we didn’t create new pages for products because the rest of the website was so out of date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equally inconvenient was the fact that the website just served as a place to host information - customers couldn’t buy our products through the website, they had to email us or go to external distributors. This doesn’t give out a good message!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my task was, at it’s core, to collate the current, up to date information and pictures for all of our products, host it on an e-commerce platform, and design a theme that is suitable for our purposes. Additional tasks would involve measuring modules to get data, editing photos, writing descriptions, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose to build the new website on top of Wordpress because it would be a familiar platform for the site’s main content authors to use. I wasn’t particularly familiar with Wordpress, WooCommerce, nor PHP, but I guess it proved to be a good opportunity to learn and expand my horizons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might seem that setting up a WooCommerce site is a simple endeavour, as ‘everything is already done for you’, but I ended up writing thousands of lines of custom PHP code in our &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;functions.php&lt;/code&gt; file, and probably hundreds more in editing templates too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When editing templates, I found it difficult to track down exactly what function created a specific part of the default WooCommerce templates sometimes. I ended up having to isolate something specific that I wanted to edit - perhaps a function name or HTML class or id - and then &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;grep&lt;/code&gt; for that string across all the files and folders in the WooCommerce plugin directory, and then work back from there to find the appropriate place to make my changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wanted a very minimal theme for the website, and I hope you’ll agree that that’s what I produced. I took some cues from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.modulargrid.net/e/modules/browser/vendor:111&quot;&gt;ModularGrid&lt;/a&gt;, and others from &lt;a href=&quot;https://synthcube.com/cart/frequency-central-en&quot;&gt;SynthCube&lt;/a&gt;, but simplified things a lot to get a nice clean look. It was really surprising to me how many of the free Wordpress / WooCommerce themes include unnecessary clutter everywhere. I didn’t like most of the themes I looked at. The clutter wasn’t very appealing, and often customers would have to jump through hoops to actually make a purchase. I didn’t want that, I wanted it to be very simple for a customer to purchase from us, so tried to avoid drop-down menus, sidebars, etc, wherever I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clutter on websites is a common problem across the web, in my opinion - I personally find even Amazon difficult to browse because the design is all over the place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/new-fcuk-website.png&quot; alt=&quot;New Frequency Central website design.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;New Frequency Central website design.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent a lot of time trying to create systems so that the data for our website could be entered in a machine readable way. I wanted to be able to generate things across the website with our data, without requiring user input. For example, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://frequencycentral.co.uk/docs/&quot;&gt;Documents&lt;/a&gt; page is updated automatically as datasheets and user guides are added to products. The same is true for the &lt;em&gt;Chipsets&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Useful Documents&lt;/em&gt; sections on the product pages. This is particularly useful for &lt;a href=&quot;https://frequencycentral.co.uk/product-tag/Bundle/&quot;&gt;Bundles&lt;/a&gt;, where the data for &lt;em&gt;Chipsets&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Useful Documents&lt;/em&gt; are imported from the bundled products, so that you don’t have to add those things a second time. I tried to ensure that there was a authoritative source for data and information, so that changing it in one place would update all of the other pages that use that information too. I really wanted to avoid pages going out of date, as that was what made our last website completely unmaintainable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also able to use the machine readable Chipset data to notify customers when they were buying products that used specialist integrated circuits. It’s important to notify them that they can purchase it from us so that they can avoid the difficulty and frustration of trying to acquire it mid-build. This was particularly important for one of our newest products, &lt;a href=&quot;https://frequencycentral.co.uk/product/stasis-leak/&quot;&gt;Stasis Leak&lt;/a&gt;, as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://frequencycentral.co.uk/product/belton-abe/&quot;&gt;Belton ABE-FX&lt;/a&gt; is incredibly new and therefore probably hard to acquire in certain countries. This notification seems to have helped many of our customers, as they purchased their integrated circuits as separate line items from us during the checkout process. It makes me smile to know that functionality I implemented was worthwhile and helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/new-fcuk-website-cart.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cart notification about potentially difficult to acquire chips.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Cart notification about potentially difficult to acquire chips.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another importance for me was to try to streamline processes for the website administrators. I was always thinking about what I could do to make using and maintaining the website easier for the folks running Frequency Central.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to simplify the WooCommerce products form, which I found to be particularly egregious. The default WooCommerce products form is a mess, and has many tabs that you have to click through to enter all of your data. If you have to click to every tab, then having a tab system isn’t saving you any time. It’s just adding extra clicks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/fcuk-newsite-tabs.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Scrolling through tabs is so unnecessary. I wanted to remove this.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Scrolling through tabs is so unnecessary. I wanted to remove this.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used CSS and JS to convert it into a simple form with no hidden sub-menus, hiding data fields that we wouldn’t be using, and revealing forms that you have to click through to access. I also took the opportunity to auto-fill data to sensible defaults that I figured we’d select most commonly. For those wondering, I chose to use client side JS and CSS rather than server side PHP because I didn’t want to edit the core WooCommerce files that generated the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A comparison of creating two product variations in the old system and the new system are show below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/fcuk-product-variation-old.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Creating WooCommerce product variations on the old system.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Old system: Trying to create two product variations in the default WooCommerce menu. Mistakes were unintentional - they happened naturally because the menu is not intuitive.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jetholt.com/assets/images/content/fcuk-product-variation-new.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Creating WooCommerce product variations on the new system.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;New system: Creating two product variations in the new menu that I edited. Nice and quick!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also implemented custom order export functionality that integrated perfectly with their workflow, to make order fulfilment quicker and less prone to errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The website &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/B5A6CiFBlTq/&quot;&gt;launched on November 19th 2019&lt;/a&gt;. Our customers were very enthusiastic to make purchases, and it completely blew away our expectations. Feedback was immensely positive across the board. I was particularly surprised at how many of the customers chose to sign up to the mailing-list to receive email updates whenever Frequency Central launched new products - within just a week FC already had more subscribers than my personal email list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frequency Central is finally in the twenty-first century!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2019 11:03:38 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://jetholt.com/new-frequency-central-website/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jetholt.com/new-frequency-central-website/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
